One question that comes up with queries with
aggregates is this: How do I do criteria based
on an aggregate. We are about to answer this and
one other question: If we use a WHERE clause,
does it go? Before or after the GROUP BY clause?
Let's answer the second question first. The WHERE
clause filters out individual records. Knowing
this, we need to ensure the WHERE clause is
used before we group columns for an aggregate.
To demonstrate this, I will add a WHERE clause
before the GROUP BY clause to limit this list
to orders that happened on or after May 1, 2014.
In executing this, we see a list of salespersons
and the amount they have sold since that date.
Having the WHERE clause is good for
individual record filtering, but what
about a group criterion? What if we wanted to
limit these results to show only salespersons
who did at least 300000 in sales during this
period? Two important points to note here:
First, we can only have one WHERE clause in a SQL
statement, so the WHERE keyword is not used again.
Secondly, this criterion needs to be placed
after the GROUP BY clause because we cannot
do aggregates until we have a group. The
keyword here is HAVING, and with this,
I will add HAVING SUM(Subtotal) >= 300000 to the
end of this query. Then, I will execute this,
and we see four people made the goal of at least
300000 in sales. To recap: The WHERE clause
filters individual records and runs before any
grouping of columns for aggregates takes place.
The HAVING clause filters based on aggregates
and is added after grouping takes place.